Gordon N. Ray Collection of Victorian Autographs
Gordon N. Ray Collection of Victorian Autographs
1721-1926
Ray, Gordon Norton, 1915-1986.
0.5 linear ft.
Collection of autographed letters, many of British politicians and statesmen of the Victorian period.
149538
Biographical History
Gordon Norton Ray (1915-1986) was a noted Victorian scholar, professor, and author. He was professor of English, specializing in Victorian literature, at Harvard (1940-1942) and then, after a brief period in the U.S. Navy during World War II, at the University of Illinois (1946-1957), where he also served as vice president and provost (1957-1960). He was also President of the John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation (1963-1985). His two-volume biography of William Makepeace Thackeray and a four-volume edition of Thackeray's letters were critically acclaimed, and his accomplishments as a major book collector led to the publication of three volumes on English and French book illustration. He also wrote extensively on H. G. Wells.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Gordon N. Ray Collection of Victorian Autographs contains autographed correspondence and autographs only, of a wide range of notable Victorian-era personalities, including authors, politicians, diplomats, churchmen, scientists, and many more. While the majority are British citizens, there are a number of Irish individuals as well as a few more exotic, such as the Turkish Ambassador to England. Dates are given as written on the document; the majority are in European format with the day preceding the month (e.g. 27/3/09 = March 27, 1909). Where possible, additional identifying information is provided for names.
Arrangement of the Collection
The autographs are subdivided into correspondence and single autographs; within this both sets of material are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has several other collections of autographs. See for example the following:
Argosy Autograph Collection
Frances Ward Harrington Autograph Collection
Graeme O'Geran Presidential Autograph Collection
Howes Norris Jr. Autograph Cartoon Collection
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- British; Politics, government and public administration; Ray, Gordon Norton, 1915- -- collector.; Autographs -- Collections.; Autographs.; Letters (correspondence)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Autographed correspondence
  - Ali - Butt, 1870-1925 (Box 1)
    Aziseel Ali (President, British Red Crescent Society), to F. Temple Esq., 24/10/25
    L.H. Amerg, to Miss Olive Mcleod, 9/2/00
    L.H. Amerg, to Miss Olive Mcleod, 27/7/03
    L.H. Amerg, to Miss Olive Mcleod, 22/10/03
    L.H. Amerg, to Miss Olive Mcleod, 20/11/03
    Margot (? Lady Astor), 11/5/06
    A.J. Balfour (Premier), 9/1/85
    Henry Balfour, to Wm. Temple, 11/6/1919
    Lord Balfour of Burleigh (Statesman)
    Bishop of Durham, 11/2/1870
    Bramwell (doctor?), to Macleod, 28/12/04
    Sir Bernard Burke, to Miss Northcote, 18/12/1874
    Mr. Issac Butt (Leader of the Irish 1876), 6/26/1876
  - Butcher - Dickson, 1831-1921 (Box 1)
    S.H. Butcher (classics Professor and writer), to Miss Olive Mcleod, 5/11/05
    Joseph Chamberlain (Tax Reformer), 5/28/?
    Sir John Chichester, 2/28/1921
    Lord Cromer, 9/7/1905
    Viscount, to F. Temple, 1/8/13?
    Danneuthier (pianist), to Miss Mcleod, 12/15/00
    W. Dargan (capitalist, railroad contractor), to F. W. Stokes Esq., 9/14/1831
    Davidson, to Miss Mcleod, 6/29/08
    Lord Derby (Foreign Secretary), to Northcote, 21/?/78
    Monseiur de Lesseps (engineer of the Suez Canal), 21/?/1876
    Charles Scott Dickson, to Dear Lady Agnes, 3/29/1910
  - Doyle - Krebz, 1829-1919 (Box 1)
    Bishop Doyle (artist), to C. Stuart, 14/8/1829
    E. M. F. ?, to Miss Forbes, 1/31/1896
    Lord George, to Miss Macleod, 7/2/?
    Mr. Gibson, Lord Ashbourne (Irish Chancellor), to Miss Macleod, 5/?/1882
    R.S. Haldane (War Office), to Miss Macleod, 8/11/1906
    Charles Halli, to Northcote, 6/27/?
    Baron Friedrich von Heigel, 8/12/1919
    Lord James of Hereford, 11/6/1906
    Jenny, to Miss Mcleod, 3/9/08
    William Jones, to Miss Mcleod, 2/1/06
    Kent, to Sir Bernard Burke, 12/18/1870
    Marie Krebz (pianist), to Miss Northcote, 5/9/1876
  - Lang - Mayo, 1869-1919 (Box 1)
    C. Lang (Bishop of Stepney), to Sir Reginald, 11/11/1886
    Mr. Holkar, Sir John (lawyer, Lord Justice), 1/28/1876
    Sir Wilfred Lawson (Temperance 1878), to Sir Stafford Northcote, 3/22/1878
    Lillian, to Mcleoud, 12/23/1888
    Sir Francis Lugard, to Wm. Temple, 12/4/1919
    S. MacNaughtan, to Olive Mcleod, 6/19/?
    S. MacNaughtan, to Olive Mcleod, 2/10/?
    S. MacNaughtan, to Olive Mcleod, 11/15/?
    S. MacNaughtan, to Olive Mcleod, 6/3/15
    John Manners (statesman), to Miss Mcleod, 2/15/1883
    Mayo, Earl of (Governor General of India, assassinated), to Sir Bernard, 5/17/1869
  - McKenna - Rosse, 1797-1909 (Box 1)
    Reginald McKenna (1863-1943, English lawyer, financier, politician), to Miss Macleod, 6/4/1906
    Viscount Milner, to Miss Macleod, 6/4/1909
    Mushrees[?] (Turkish Ambassador), to Sir Strafford, Oct/16/1876
    Mr. John O'Donovan (Home Ruler), to Sir Bernard, May 23, 1855
    O'Hagan (Irish Chancellor), to Sir Bernard, June 14, 1874
    Lord Plunkett (Mr. Wm Plunkett), to Deed, May 26, 1797
    Sir Henry Rawlinson (India Office, Asiatic researcher), to Sir Stafford Northcote, Feb. 29, 1872
    Lord Hugh Richard Heathcote Cecil (1869-1956, M.P., etc), to Sir Reginald Mcleod, Dec. 10, 1906
    Fernando De los Rios, to Oliva Temple, April 14, 1926
    Fernando De los Rios, to Mrs. C. L. Temple, May 19, ?
    Lord Roberts, to Mrs. Macleod, Mar. 1908
    Lord Rosse (astronomer), to Mrs. Macleod, Feb. 20, 1865
  - Salisbury - Sutherland, 1873-1915 (Box 1)
    Lord Salisbury (Prime Minister), to Miss MacLeod, Aug. 14, 1887
    Col. Sanderson (M.P., Irish politician), to Wm. MacLeod, Feb. 5, 1888
    Count Schowalobf (Russian Ambassador, Russo-Turk War), June 5, ?
    Earl of Selborne, to Olive MacLeod, Jan. 2, 1900
    Earl of Selborne, to Olive MacLeod, Feb. 20, 1901
    B.K.C. Sen, to Mrs. Hobhouse, 1/7/1873
    Tom Shaw (1872-1938, Labor leader), to Mrs. Hobhouse, ? 20/ 1906
    Mrs. Sidgwick, to Mrs. Hobhouse, Sept. 8, 1903
    Sir John A. Simon, to Mrs. Hobhouse, Mar. 1, 1908
    Sir John A. Simon, to Lady Agnes ?, June 22, 1909
    Sir John A. Simon, to Mrs. Temple, May 31, 1915
    W.H. Smith (Leader of the House) and Miss Cornelia Sorabji (First Woman advocate) (enclosed phamplet), to W. Macleod, Feb. 6, ?
    Dean Stanley (author), Mar. 5, ?77
    Lord Strathcona, to Lady MacLeod, Mar. 21, 1906
    Mr. R. S. Strutt (scientist), to Miss MacLeod, Feb. 25, ?
    D. of Sutherland, to Miss MacLeod, Ap. 27, 1905
  - Violin - Yeo, 1721-1926 (Box 1)
    Violin Tree, to Olive MacLeod
    J. B. Trend, to Mrs. Temple, May 15, 1923
    J. B. Trend, to Mrs. Temple, Sept. 15, 1926
    Sir Charles Walston (orginally Waldstein, 1856-1927, born NY City, archaeologist and naturalist, British subject, to Miss MacLeod, Ap. 29, 1909
    Baron Ward (diplomat in Duke of Lucais[?]'s service at Parma), to B. Burke Esq., Nov. 29, 1868
    Weil, to Miss MacLeod, Nov. 19, 1906
    Sir George S. White, to Miss MacLeod, Mar. 11, 1908
    [Samuel] Wiberforce (Bishop of Winchester)
    [Richard] Yeo (medallist and engraver), to Robert Pitt Esq., Feb. 29, 1721
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, unsigned, 10 pieces (Box 1)
- Autographs
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    Duke of Abercorn
    Leonard Borwich
    H. Carleton (Irish novelist)
    Lord Carlisle (statesman, orator, writer)
    John Cimon
    Benjamin Disraeli (Chancellor of Exchequer)
    H. Grattan (Irish statesman, Grattan's Parliament)
    Arthur T. Thrupp
    The Lady Northcote (Princess Louise ?)
    The Right Hon. Sir S. Northcote Bart M.P.
    Wm. Stuart
    Mr. Wynn, Lord Oswald (Conservative Whip)